Thank you.
I have the privilege of being one of the pastors here this morning.
Super excited that you have joined us this morning.
We are launching a brand new series, which I will talk about in just a minute.
But for now, I want to recap where we've been this far this year.
So we just finished up nine weeks of the spiritual formation, spiritual practices series.
And the whole point of that series, and it's going to continue on and off for a while, is that we be with Jesus in order to become like Jesus so that we can do what he did, right?
And so far, we've talked about prayer.
We've talked about fasting.
I've heard many stories from many of you who have tried new different types of prayer.
Maybe you've tried fasting or some version of fasting, or you brought a new rhythm of fasting into your life.
And I just want to remind all of us that the whole point of this is to pursue Jesus in relationship.
That's what the whole point of this thing is all about.
We are a church of real people with real lives that are trying to form a Christ-centered community.
We want to know Jesus by spending time with Jesus in order to become like Jesus so that we can show others what he's like in the world.
So I hope that you don't just incorporate these things in your life for eight weeks and then forget about them and wait until the next series to try the new thing.
I hope, I pray, that you would consider to continue these rhythms in your life if they are helping you pursue Jesus.
If they are not, then put them on a shelf somewhere until later and find something else that helps you pursue Jesus.
Sound good?
All right.
This week, we turn our attention to the Easter narrative.
We are starting a three-week series in preparation for Easter Sunday called A Living Savior.
Christians, myself included, we tend to gravitate towards the cross.
Right?
Calvary is enough.
It's a beautiful thing.
We just sang about it.
And it's great that we gravitate towards the cross because Jesus said on the cross, it is finished.
But cross means nothing apart from the resurrection.
So, what does it look like for us as Christians to submit to a risen Savior who accomplishes his victory, his life, the whole thing, the whole point?
He accomplished it through death and then resurrection.
And isn't it like that for our lives?
Don't often we find resurrection on the other side of sorrow, pain, heartache, loss.
We celebrate, we worship, we submit to a Savior who accomplishes victory through death.
So, the next three weeks, we're going to focus on a living Savior.
Let's pray and then we will get started.
Father, we are so grateful again for this opportunity to set everything aside.
All of our worries, all of our fears, all of our anxieties, all of our sin.
And lay it at your feet.
Set our minds' attention on you this morning.
Holy Spirit, I pray that you would be at work in this room through my words, through the reading of Scripture.
God, just doing supernatural things to draw us to yourself.
God, we want to know you more.
So, lead us this time, this morning, for your glory and for our good.
It's in Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
If you have your Bibles, I'd love for you to turn to Mark chapter 14.
Mark chapter 14 is going to be our text for this morning.
And Mercer's out of town, and somehow I made it to church without the Bible that I like to preach with.
So, that happened.
So, I found this in Lost and Found.
So, if it's yours, I'm sorry.
And thank you for letting me borrow it.
And you can have it back after service.
Okay.
It's a nice Bible.
If you don't come get it, I might keep it.
So, if you would, I'd love for you, once you get there, to stand, and we will read this passage of Scripture together.
Mark 14, starting in verse 1.
And after two days, it was the Passover and the Feast of the Unleavened Bread, and the chief priests and the scribes sought how they might take him, this being Jesus, by trickery and put Jesus to death.
But they said, not during the feast, lest there be an uproar of the people.
And being in Bethany at the house of Simon the leopard, as Jesus sat at the table, a woman came, having an alabaster flask of very costly oil, of spikenard.
Then she broke, she broke the flask, and she poured it on his head.
There were some there who were indignant among themselves and said, why was this fragrant oil wasted?
Wasted.
For it might have been sold for more than 300 denarii or close to a year's salary and given to the poor.
But Jesus said, let her alone.
Why do you trouble her?
She has done a good work for me.
For you have the poor with you always, and wherever you wish, you may do good to them.
But me, you do not always have.
She has done what she could.
She has come beforehand to anoint my body for burial.
Assuredly, I say to you, wherever the gospel is preached.
Listen to this.
Assuredly, I say to you, wherever the gospel is preached in the whole world, what this woman has done will also be told as a memorial to her.
Then Judas Iscariot, one of the twelve, went to the chief priest to betray him to them.
And when they heard it, they were glad.
And they promised to give him money.
So he sought how he might conveniently betray him.
This is the word of the Lord.
We're getting there.
All right, you can be seated.
I don't know about you.
Some of you are probably familiar with this story on some level or another.
I grew up in church, went to a Bible college.
So I'm familiar with the story.
It's told here in Mark.
It's also told in John.
And the woman in Mark here is an unnamed woman.
But John names her as Mary, the sister of Lazarus.
So if you don't mind, I'm just going to call her Mary the rest of the morning.
Just so that it's convenient and easy for us to grasp.
But no matter how familiar you might be with the story, something strikes me as odd.
Well, there's a lot of things that strike me as odd in the passage because I don't live in first century, you know.
So breaking oil, pouring it on a guy's head, all of that's weird.
But here's the thing that most strikes me as odd.
Verse 9.
Assuredly, I say to you, wherever, this is Jesus, wherever the gospel is preached,
in the whole world, for all time, what this woman has done will be told as a memorial to her?
Is that odd to anybody else or just to me?
Alright, pretty weird, right?
Depending on your familiarity with this story and your personality,
you might view this moment, this woman breaking this expensive perfume bottle and dumping it all over Jesus.
And John says that she then moves from his head to his feet and uses her hair to wipe his feet.
Depending on your familiarity, your personality,
you either view this as like a beautiful gesture from a loving disciple,
or an insane move by an attention-seeking crazy person, right?
Shattering a 12-ounce jar of strong perfume and dumping it on an unsuspecting rabbi at a dinner party.
That's kind of a party foul, right?
Anybody else like, hey, you just ruined everyone's night.
So, wherever you fall on the spectrum of responses,
I think we can all agree that it seems weird that Jesus editorializes this moment in this way.
He pauses everything to focus on this woman's action,
and he says, wherever the gospel is preached for all time,
all across the world,
this woman's story will be told as a memorial to her.
I don't know about you,
but of all the stories and all the Gospels,
this story does not make my top 10 list of the stories that should be told all over the world,
everywhere, wherever the gospel is preached.
Am I the only one?
Okay, I'm the only one.
Cool.
I mean, casting out demons, healing blind,
making the lame walk,
resurrecting people from the dead.
Why is Jesus so set on this story lasting for thousands of years?
What might,
my notes say,
what might we be missing?
But it sounds like I'm the only one with a problem here.
So,
what might I be missing that makes this story so profound for all people,
for all time?
What makes this story so integral in telling the story of the gospel?
This is our overarching task for the morning.
What is Jesus emphasizing about this woman's actions?
And what impact might it have on our lives and our telling of the gospel?
Sound good?
All right.
So, in order to get there,
we need to examine,
what do we do in Bible study?
Context, right?
We need to examine the context to get a foundation for why her actions are so important.
Because the reality is her actions are in stark contrast to all the other characters in the passage.
So, verse 1.
This is,
just for timeline's sake,
after Lazarus was raised from the dead,
that's why we read that passage in worship,
about a week before Jesus is going to be crucified,
a couple days before Jesus is going to be crucified.
So, after two days,
it was the Passover,
at the Feast of the Unleavened Bread,
and the chief priests and the scribes,
two different groups,
two different categories of people,
they came together
to see how they might take Jesus
by trickery
and put him
to death.
So,
we got two groups of characters here
that are plotting against Jesus.
What is their motivation?
Why might they be plotting against Jesus?
Two groups,
chief priests
and the scribes.
Again,
this is the final week of Christ's life on earth.
The tension around Christ's life and his teachings is increasing.
The temperature is rising in the room.
Everyone knows something has to happen.
He's raised a person from the dead.
That tends to raise the emotional energy in the room, right?
We know this.
Those of us that believe in a resurrected Savior
have conversations with atheist friends
or people that reject Jesus
and we claim,
hey,
he rose from the dead.
What happens?
Emotions rise, right?
Because somebody thinks we're nuts
and we're like,
nope,
I've seen it.
I've experienced it.
It's happened.
And everyone else is like,
you're nuts.
Emotional temperature rises.
And so that's what's going on here.
And this all comes to a head
with Lazarus being raised from the dead.
Now,
we don't have time for a full history lesson
around Jewish culture,
how the temple and the priests and the Pharisees
and how they all work together this morning.
And even if we had time,
guess who's probably not the most qualified person
to give you that lesson?
Me.
Okay.
All right.
But I'll give you some overarching realities here.
Chief priests,
they are predominantly Sadducees
and the Sadducees were in charge
of running the temple in Jerusalem.
Okay.
So they like oversaw the temple in Jerusalem.
Their ancestors were an integral part
in striking a political deal
with the Romans
that allowed the Jews
to continue to worship God in the temple.
The Jews were the only group in the Roman world
that were allowed to just worship their God
and ignore the Roman gods, right?
And the chief priests,
their family members,
their ancestors were the ones
that made this alliance with Rome
so that they could continue
worshiping God in the temple.
Does that sound like a pretty good thing?
Okay.
It does sound like a pretty good thing,
but it wasn't
because the Sadducees,
they really weren't concerned
about worshiping God properly
as much as they were concerned
about the wealth,
cultural influence,
and power
that came with them
running the temple,
having this political alliance with Rome.
They were quite literally
married to Rome
and they were using
their relationship with Rome
to get wealth,
influence, power.
Essentially,
they turned the temple
into a religious business
that made the chief priests
and the Sadducees
very wealthy
and important.
See what their agenda
might be here with Jesus?
They've got an agenda.
Jesus seems to be getting
in the way of that agenda.
You heard Caiaphas
in the worship reading.
He said,
if Jesus keeps doing this,
the Romans are going to come in
and they're not going to let us
keep doing the things
that we've been doing.
That's a problem
to the bottom line.
to our status,
our wealth,
our power,
our influence.
Let's just kill the guy
so that we can keep doing things
the way that we want to do things,
so that we can keep getting
the money
and the power
and the wealth
that we track in.
Okay,
so the chief priests,
politically motivated.
They're really concerned
about their power,
their wealth,
their status.
The scribes
were predominantly Pharisees
and most of us
who grew up in church
know a little bit more
about the Pharisees
than we do about the Sadducees
because Jesus spent
most of his time
with the Pharisees.
They were very concerned
with doctrinal
and theological purity.
They were obsessed
with the Old Testament law
and they believed
if the majority
of the nation of Israel,
if they could get
the majority
of the nation of Israel
to obey God's law perfectly,
that God would send Messiah.
And so they were
constantly preaching
about the Old Testament law,
holding people accountable
to the Old Testament law.
This is why they had
no compassion
for sinners
and tax collectors
because they said,
you're the reason
Messiah has not come.
Messiah won't come
until you guys
get your act together.
Listen to us.
Do what we say
and Messiah will come.
Now,
here's the interesting thing
about those two groups.
They seem
like very opposite
ends of the spectrum, right?
One group
is far more concerned
with political power,
influence, money.
They kind of use
the temple,
not really because
they want to worship God,
but because
what they can get from it.
Make sense?
And then the Pharisees
love God
with all of their mind.
They really want
to get it right.
They're obsessed
with the Old Testament,
but here's where
these two groups intersect.
Guess what the Old Testament
says Jewish people
have to do?
They've got to go
to the temple.
Who's in charge
of the temple?
Sadducees.
They're in charge
of the temple
and the Pharisees know
not good guys,
but they need
the temple
to obey the law.
Right?
Make sense?
And so there's
this weird partnership
between the chief priest
and the scribes
where the chief priests
are like,
hey, you guys
keep telling people
that they have to come
to our temple
and offer sacrifices
and we'll keep
like double charging
them in the courts
and make them pay
all of this money
for our animals
to sacrifice
at our temple.
We'll keep getting rich
and you guys
can feel good
about morality
and all that stuff
and it's just
a partnership
that they had
to have together.
Both groups
needed each other
for their own agendas
and at this point
in Jesus' story,
the agenda of Jesus
and the agenda
of the chief priests
and the scribes
are at total odds
with one another.
Jesus is getting
in the way
because the scribes
see it as a threat
to them getting rich,
having wealth,
power,
and status.
Wait,
I got that backwards.
The chief priests,
sorry.
You guys paying attention
because if I get it wrong
and then you think
I got it right,
then you got it wrong.
All right?
Cool.
So,
the chief priests
are like,
he's getting in the way,
he's going to ruin everything,
the Romans aren't going
to trust us anymore,
they're just going
to take over the temple,
which would have been
easy for Rome to do.
Like, hey,
you're done,
stop it.
We're in charge here now.
We'll put our gods
in this temple
and you guys can leave.
And the scribes
feel like Jesus
is teaching false narratives.
He literally said,
tear down this temple
and I'll rebuild it
in three days.
That's blasphemy
and he should be killed
because he's leading people
astray from the truth.
So,
we see how Jesus' agenda
is at odds
with both of these agendas.
Okay.
Jesus was threatening
the peace
that the Romans counted on
and the chief priests
to keep in Jerusalem.
According to the scribes,
Jesus was leading people astray
from the obedience
of the law.
He was working
on the Sabbath,
eating with tax collectors
and sinners.
Okay.
So,
all of that to say,
is it possible
that some of us
in this room
might have similar issues
with Jesus?
We can't seem
to make the Jesus
of the Bible
fit our agendas.
So,
our only option
is to reject him
or to relegate him
to a good moral teacher
that I can learn
some things from
but certainly
isn't God
in the flesh
and certainly
can't have total authority
over the decisions
of my life.
So,
let me make some
cultural application here.
The chief priests,
they were cool with Jesus
until he got in the way
of their desired life
of comfort,
success,
wealth,
importance,
and status.
They were fully integrated
into the secular culture.
They wanted to have
the temple
and everything else.
The Pharisees
were cool with Jesus
as long as his teachings
aligned with their
systematic theology.
At the heart of both
of these groups,
issues with Jesus
is they had an agenda
for their lives
and he was getting
in the way.
So,
two ways I see this
play out in American
Christianity.
Cultural Christianity.
For a long time
in America,
Christianity was the
predominant majority
worldview of our culture.
This has created,
in my opinion,
an environment
where a lot of people,
especially in counties
like Frederick County,
Bible Belt light,
right?
Right?
Okay.
We love to wear
the badge of Christian.
I'm a Christian.
You're a Christian.
We're all Christians.
But many of us
who wear the badge
of Christian
aren't really interested
in the Jesus of the Bible
having authority
for my decision making.
Okay?
And that's many of us
in this room.
Some of us in this room.
We struggle with this.
We wear the badge
of Christianity
because it's what
our parents did.
It's what our families do.
It's what people
in the South do.
But when Jesus
gets in our business
and tells us
what we have to do,
we've got a problem
because we want Jesus
and everything else.
Okay.
Moral Christianity.
Another popular group
in the American church
is those who want
to legislate
the morality of others
using the Bible
as their foundation.
However,
their commitment
to biblical morality
causes them
to be unkind
and unloving
to people
who disagree with them.
does this group
exist
in any of our hearts?
Are we more concerned
with morality,
the morality of others,
than laying down
our lives
in obedience
to Jesus?
Do any of us
have the heart posture
of the scribes
or
the chief priests?
Is it possible
that these attitudes
might creep
into our lives?
I think it's so important
that we consider
these things
because here's what
we do with stories
like this.
We read stories
like this
and at worst,
like at the absolute
worst thing we could do
is we could make
ourselves the hero
of the story.
Like we read the story
and we're feeling
real good about ourselves
and we're like,
yeah,
I would do what
Mary did,
right?
I would be breaking
that glass
and dumping it
on Jesus.
Everybody else
is acting a fool.
I would be Mary.
Now,
if we're honest,
some of us,
we've been in church
long enough
that we know
that we're not Mary
but we're definitely
not the bad people
in the story.
So what we tend to do
is we read these stories
as like casual observers
who are in the room
and we're better
than the bad guys
but not as good
as the good guy.
Anybody read their Bible
like that?
Or is that just me?
All right,
cool.
So what I want to do
this morning
is I want us to consider
is it possible
that actually
at times
and maybe even more often
than we'd like
to admit
our heart
actually resonates
more with some
of the bad characters
in the story
than just a casual observer.
Is it possible
that some of us
are concerned
with wealth,
power,
status,
reputation
and we want Jesus
as long as we can
have Jesus
in that stuff?
Is it possible
that our love
for Jesus
has caused us
to care so much
about other people's
morality
that when we preach
the gospel
we preach it
bent towards judgment
and wrath
and condemnation
and we're unkind
and we're unloving
and no one
who doesn't know Jesus
wants to be around us?
Is it possible?
Okay,
so there's our first
two characters.
We having fun yet?
This one was tough
for me.
All right,
next group
is the disciples
in the room
and being in Bethany
at the house
of Simon the leper
Jesus sat at the table
a woman came
having an alabaster flask
of very costly oil.
She broke the flask
poured it on his head.
There were some
who were indignant
among themselves
mad,
angry,
frustrated.
Why was this
fragrant oil
wasted
for it might
have been sold
for more than
a year's salary
and given
to the poor?
Not only did they
have this thought
in their mind
but they criticized
her sharply.
They had a judgmental
thought and then
they acted on it.
So outside the room
is a group of religious
and political leaders
who are seeking
to kill Jesus
because he's getting
in the way
of their agenda.
But inside the room
is a group of people
who have given up
a lot to follow Jesus.
Right?
They've given up
a lot to be
in this room.
They're following
after Jesus
and they take issue
with this woman's actions
because they're convinced,
listen to this,
this is going to be hard
for me
because it's me,
they're convinced
that they know
what Christ's agenda
for this woman's life is
and it certainly isn't.
This woman
had taken a year's salary
and essentially ruined
everyone's night.
Certainly Jesus
wouldn't want this.
He wouldn't want
this money
to be used this way.
Imagine how many
poor people
could have been fed.
This group
of Christ followers
were self-righteous
and judgmental.
They were slow
to listen
and they were quick
to speak
to get angry.
I want to camp out here
for a little bit
because I think
this is probably
the predominant issue
with the type
of people
that gather
at Canvas Community Church.
I'm sure we have
some cultural Christians
that want all
of the world
plus Jesus.
I'm sure we have
some religiously
morally motivated people
that want to
self-righteously
condemn everyone else
but I think more
than those two categories
we have this category.
People that have
given up a lot
to follow Jesus
have followed Jesus
for some time
but in their
following of Jesus
they've been convinced
that what they've
heard from God
their interpretation
of the Scripture
is 100% right
and everyone else
should follow things
the way that we
follow things
and if they don't
we're going to
tell them about it.
Many of us
have been following
Jesus for a while
we've heard all
the sermons
we know all
the Sunday school
answers
and we're pretty
sure we have
a good handle
on what God's like.
We tend to look
at other
so-called Christians
who have heard
different sermons
from different
perspectives
and we become
self-righteous
and judgmental.
We're quite confident
that God sees things
the same way
that we see things
and we're unwilling
to take any time
at all
to pause
and consider
what God
might actually
think
about that
perspective.
I'm going to
step on some
toes.
Okay.
I got off
Facebook
I guess
close to a month
ago
and it just so
happened to be
right around Lent
and I think
everyone just
assumed that I
got off Facebook
for Lent
but I didn't
get off Facebook
for Lent.
Can I tell you
why I got off
Facebook?
I didn't hear
what it was
but it might
have been funny.
There's this
game called
the Super Bowl
anybody heard
of it?
Okay.
So the Super Bowl
was on
and there's
this commercial
that came on
called He Gets Us.
Anybody heard
of it?
Okay.
So a commercial
about Jesus
showed on the
Super Bowl
within hours
I got on my
Facebook news feed
and my Facebook
news feed
literally
and this is
probably because
I'm a pastor
so it shows
like what my
algorithms are
like.
My news feed
was filled
with angry
arguments between
Christians on
both sides of
the aisle.
All 100%
convinced that
their perspective
about the ad
was the right
perspective about
the ad.
100%
convinced that
what they
thought about
the ad
is what God
thought about
the ad.
Both
within moments
they didn't
take time
to think
they didn't
take time
to pray
they didn't
take time
to do
any research
immediately
social media
I'm right
you're wrong
man
if Jesus
was around
they would
have not
used this
money for
an ad
they would
have given
it to the
poor.
Anybody
have that
on their
timeline?
okay
man
if Jesus
was around
he would
have really
wanted that
ad to be
more clear
it just
watered down
the gospel
it's confusing
everybody
what a waste
of money
okay
listen
I do not
bring this
up to draw
any specific
conclusions
about the
ad
we can have
that conversation
later
I bring it
up
as a cultural
commentary
on the
self-righteous
and judgmental
spirit that is
alive and well
in the American
church
and I
had to
get off
Facebook
because I
couldn't
stomach it
anymore
is it
possible
that we
might at
times miss
God's agenda
in the name
of God
becoming so
convinced
that God's
agenda aligns
with ours
proof texting
the Bible
to make it
agree with
our intended
outcomes
church in
America is
so divided
because we're
convinced that
we're right
and they're
wrong
more quick
to speak
self-righteously
separating
ourselves
and casting
judgments on
our brothers
and sisters
with different
perspectives than
ours
this is exactly
what this group
of disciples
did and Jesus
rebukes them
for it
look he
acknowledges
their heart
for the poor
he quotes the
passage that's
all about taking
care of the
poor
he's like
you're there
you get it
this is important
to me
taking care of
poor people
is important
to me
you're always
going to have
poor people
to take care
of but I'm
about to go
to the cross
and die
and this woman's
the only one
that seems to be
paying attention
maybe Jesus
needs to rebuke
some of us
this morning
for the same
heart posture
Matthew 7
this is the last
thing I posted
before I got
off Facebook
judge not
that you may
not be judged
for with
the judgment
you pronounce
you will be
judged
and with the
measure you use
it will be
measured to you
why do you
seek the speck
that is in
your brother's
eye
but not
notice the
log that
is in
your own
eye
or how
can you
say to
your brother
let me
take the
speck out
of your
eye
when there's
a log
in your
own eye
you hypocrite
first take
the log
out of your
own eye
and then
you will
see clearly
to take
the speck
out of
your brother's
eye
I'm going
to walk
out
on a pretty
sturdy
limb here
and say
that most
of us
in this
room
myself
at the
top
of the
list
have
judgmentally
and self
righteously
missed God
in the
name of
God
and I
think
the word
that I
have for
all of us
this morning
is that we
just need to
slow down a
little bit
we live
in a
world of
hot takes
where everybody
needs to know
your opinion
on every
situation
immediately
the kingdom
of God
is so
much bigger
than we
think
and so
maybe it
might take
us a
little bit
longer
than like
90 seconds
to come
up with
an opinion
on something
what if we
just slowed
down
we didn't
have to
have an
opinion
on everything
immediately
what if we
sought the
Scriptures
together
in community
with people
that we
trusted
and that we
loved
and we
were willing
to disagree
on the
things that
were outside
clearly the
gospel
James 1
know this
my beloved
brothers
let every
person
be quick
to hear
slow
to speak
to get
angry
for the
anger
of man
does not
produce
the
righteousness
of God
therefore
put away
all filthiness
and rampant
wickedness
and receive
with meekness
with humility
the implanted
word which
is able
to save
your souls
so
characters
in the story
up to this
point
they're plotting
to kill
Jesus
because he's
in the way
of their
selfish agendas
or they're
condemning
and judging
this obedient
woman
because they're
blinded by
their own
piety
and certainty
every group
so far
is convinced
that they know
what God's
agenda is
or that
their agenda
is more
important
than God's
agenda
they're
in direct
rebellion
to the
agenda
of God
and again
we're rarely
the heroes
of the story
we're rarely
just casual
observers
most of the
time
more often
than not
when we read
the Scriptures
we're actually
in some way
shape or form
the villain
one of the
villains
so
as we continue
consider which
one of the
villains in the
story
your heart
resonates
with
most
and if
it's
more
than
one
that's
okay
because
I've
got
more
than
one
too
okay
so
one more
character
before we
get to the
answer
of the
question
that we
started
with
which is
why does
God
Jesus
think
Mary's
sacrifice
is so
awesome
God
by the
name
of
Judas
verse
I'm not
going to
belabor
this point
because I
think
at the
heart
of what
Judas
is
struggling
with
is
very
similar
to the
heart
of the
Sadducees
the chief
priests
the only
difference
here is
the
Sadducees
refused
to follow
Jesus
because
their
wealth
status
and
power
what
Judas
did
is
he
followed
Jesus
thinking
that
following
Jesus
would
get him
wealth
status
and
power
does that
make sense
so it's a
very similar
heart
posture
here
one
rejects
Jesus
because
they
know
he's
going to
their
wealth
status
power
success
the
good
life
which
is
not
the
good
life
that's
why
I
did
and
Judas
is
following
Jesus
thinking
I'm
going to
be one
of the
right
hand
men
to the
Messiah
right
what
is
the
Messiah
what
do
they
think
the
Messiah
is
going
to
do
he's
going
to
take
over
everything
he's
going
to be
in
charge
right
hand
dudes
to
the
guy
that's
in
charge
that's
going
to
give
me
what
wealth
power
status
success
like
all
of it
however
the
closer
that
Jesus
got
to
Jerusalem
during
the
Passover
week
the
more
apparent
it
became
to
Judas
that
Jesus
either
wasn't
the
Messiah
or
at
least
not
the
Messiah
that
he
was
hoping
for
so
he
leveraged
his
access
to
Jesus
in
order
to
get
some
of
the
power
wealth
and
the
status
that
he
was
hoping
for
again
before
we
start
throwing
stones
to
Judas
maybe
some
of
us
in
this
room
can
relate
maybe
we
said
yes
to
Jesus
and
when
we
said
yes
to
Jesus
we
thought
it
was
going
to
mean
one
thing
and
it
so
far
turned
out
to
mean
something
totally
different
maybe
we're
disappointed
or angry
with
God
maybe
we're
even
on
the
brink
of
walking
away
from
God
altogether
because
he
isn't
the
savior
that
we
thought
he
would
be
I've
been
walking
with
Jesus
long
enough
that
I
think
can
confidently
say
this
statement
Jesus
isn't
always
the
God
we
want
but
he
is
always
the
God
that
we
need
can
trust
him
and
resurrection
life
victory
often
comes
on the
other
side
of
death
and
defeat
because
the
savior
that
we
worship
the
Lord
that
feet
of
wins
victory
over
sin
after
death
and
defeat
so
Judas
shows
up
Judas
shows
us
that
getting
what
we
want
doesn't
always
lead
to
what
we
think
it
will
the
sad
story
of
Judas
is
after
he
betrays
Jesus
gets
the
wealth
power
the
status
that
he
thought
so
desperately
wanted
leaves
him
empty
ends
up
taking
his
own
life
I
think
that's
a
helpful
reminder
for
many
of
us
that
if
we
keep
chasing
after
the
things
of
this
world
often
it's
like
grasping
after
the
wind
we
get
the
thing
that
we
thought
needed
to
have
success
to
have
security
to
be
happy
and
we're
still
not
happy
next
thing
on
the
horizon
well
if
I
just
get
this
thing
then
I'll
be
happy
if
I
just
get
this
thing
then
I'll
be
happy
and
it
just
never
works
okay
this is
where the
story gets
fun and
uplifting
is that
good
okay
so we've
got people
all over
this story
that are
their agenda
is at
odds with
God's
agenda
and
they're
either
rebelling
against
him
trying
to
kill
him
or
just
being
judgmental
and
totally
missing
the
mark
and
then
we
have
Mary
surrounded
by a
crowd
of
individuals
fighting
against
God's
agenda
with
their
own
agenda
we
can
begin
to
appreciate
why
Jesus
made
such
a
big
deal
of
Mary's
actions
chapter
verse
she
breaks
the
she breaks
it
the expensive
bottle
she could
have
poured
some
of
it
she
shatters
it
all
over
his
head
all
over
his
feet
like
this
is
like
crazy
and
they're
mad
and
he says
let her
alone
why
do
you
trouble
her
she
has
done
a
good
work
for
me
you
always
have
the
poor
with
you
and
whenever
you
wish
can
do
something
for
them
but
me
will
not
always
have
she
done
what
she
could
has
come
before
me
to
anoint
my
body
for
burial
assuredly
I
say
to
you
wherever
the
gospel
is
preached
in the
whole
world
what
this
woman
has
done
will
also
be
told
as
a
memorial
to
her
again
surrounded
by
people
fighting
God's
agenda
Mary
is
fully
submitted
to
God's
agenda
her
actions
clearly
demonstrate
two
markers
of
discipleship
to
Jesus
that
lasts
I
usually
don't
do
sermon
titles
that's
my
sermon
title
this
morning
discipleship
that
lasts
he
says
from
now
on
forever
when
the
gospel
is
preached
we're
going
to
talk
about
this
woman
why
because
she
exemplifies
two
markers
of
discipleship
that
lasts
number
one
sacrificial
worship
Mary
unapologetically
shatters
a 12
ounce
bottle
of
extremely
expensive
oil
to
pour
on
Christ's
head
and
his
feet
the
breaking
of
the
bottle
and
the
using
of
its
entire
content
shows
no
regard
for
what
this
offering
will
cost
her
Jesus
is
worth
the
best
of
what
she
has
to
give
and
it
fills
the
room
with
the
aroma
of
her
sacrificial
worship
everyone
there's
no
hiding
this
act
of
worship
everyone
knows
that
she
has
sacrificed
up
close
to
a
year's
salary
it
reminds
me
of
King
David
dancing
before
the
Lord
with
no
concern
of
what
people
would
think
about
him
Mary
was
caught
up
in
her
realization
of
the
beauty
and
majesty
of
God
in
the
flesh
she
has
come
to
understand
the
incredible
and
unconditional
love
of
the
God
who
created
her
standing
right
in
front
of
her
and
overwhelmed
by
his
presence
the
only
appropriate
response
for her
was
worship
with
reckless
abandon
oh that
we would
comprehend
the beauty
of Christ's
love for
us
and respond
with
sacrificial
worship
so
first
marker
sacrificial
worship
second
marker
total
surrender
to
God's
agenda
verse
eight
she
has
done
what
she
could
has
come
before
to
anoint
my
body
for
burial
we
can't
miss
this
again
Mary
seems
to be
the
only
one
that
gets
what
Jesus
is
talking
about
the
only
one
who
understands
what's
about
to
happen
Jesus
seems
to
indicate
that
Mary
understands
that
he's
going
to
have
die
and
she
therefore
prepares
his
body
for
burial
not
only
is she
worshiping
sacrificially
but
she's
fully
submitted
to
God's
agenda
which
is
in
stark
contract
to
the
rest
of
the
characters
of
the
story
she's
willing
to
worship
serve
to
surrender
her
life
to
a
savior
that
she
knows
is
going
to
die
that's
not
how
Messiah
is
supposed
to
work
she
doesn't
fully
understand
it
but
she's
willing
to
submit
Jesus
she's
seen
his
resurrection
power
when he
raised
Lazarus
from
the
dead
she
is
willing
to
trust
him
even
if
it
doesn't
look
the way
she
thought
it
would
look
this
is
discipleship
are
we
willing
to
trust
Jesus
even
if
it
doesn't
look
like
we
think
it
should
look
are
we
willing
to
be
obedient
to
him
even
if
the
results
we're
getting
are
not
the
results
that
we
deserve
are
we
willing
to
lay
everything
down
at
his
feet
because
he's
proven
to
be
trustworthy
he
might
not
be
the
God
that
we
want
Mary
has
a
track
record
for
kind
of
being
in
the
right
spot
doing
the
right
thing
and
earlier
another
story
we get
of
Mary
and
Martha
her
sister
Martha
is
in
the
kitchen
doing
all
the
hospitality
actions
we
remember
the
story
some
of
us
Mary
is
sitting
at
the
feet
of
Jesus
that
language
sitting
at
the
feet
of
Jesus
is
the
language
used
of
disciples
the
Scripture
puts
Mary
in
the
this
world
women
do
not
disciple
under
men
Mary
positions
herself
as
a
disciple
of
Jesus
welcomes
feet
as
he
teaches
and
earlier
Jesus
taught
very
clearly
Mark
chapter
verse
and
he
began
to
teach
them
who
his
disciples
I
believe
Mary
would
have
caught
wind
of
this
teaching
whether
she
heard
it
directly
from
Jesus
or
passed
down
chief
priest
and
the
scribes
wow
is this
sounding
familiar
king
of
the
universe
kind
of
knows
what's
going
to
happen
in
the
future
is that
crazy
okay
chief
priest
and
scribes
to be
killed
and
after
three
days
rise
again
and
he
said
this
confusingly
so that
no one
knew
what he
meant
what
did
he
say
said
it
plainly
he
taught
his
disciples
that
the
chief
priest
and
the
scribes
were going to kill him and he was going to rise again. Mary gets it. She may not fully grasp what everything's going on but she understands what Jesus has come to Jerusalem to do and she gives everything she has to prepare him to submit her agenda, to submit her resources, to submit her life to his agenda. This is discipleship that lasts. Are we willing to lay down everything we have at the feet of Jesus and trust what he's doing?
and be willing to follow him to do? Are we fully surrendered to God's agenda? Are we fully surrendered to God's agenda? Or do we have the posture of the chief priests or the scribes or Judas or the disciples? Do we often find ourselves at odds with God's agenda? Because our agenda doesn't line up with his agenda. Mary seems to be one of the first
disciples of the first disciples of Jesus to understand what we have to do. She's willing to do that. She clearly demonstrates with this action that she is willing to surrender her life to a crucified Savior. That sounds insane. Submit your life to a crucified Savior?
1 Corinthians. The cross is foolishness to those who are perishing. But to us who are being saved, it is the power of God. Submitting your life to a crucified Savior is the best thing that any of us can do.
Because he's not just a crucified Savior. He's a resurrected Savior proving that he is worthy of all of our attention, of all of our resources, of all of our agendas. His agenda now becomes the only agenda that matters.
How many of us can say that we are genuinely willing to submit to God's agenda, even if it looks like death, defeat, and loss?
Saying this to myself, if you're feeling really bad about yourself, I'm not condemning you. This is me.
How often do we actually believe that dying to ourselves and submitting to God's agenda leads to life?
Later, right after Jesus taught about him dying, in Mark 8, he says this, calling to the crowds and to his disciples, he said,
If anyone would come after me, if anyone would disciple after me, let him deny himself and take up his cross and follow me.
For whoever would save his life will lose it, but whoever loses his life for my sake will find it.
For what does it profit a man to gain the whole world?
Do you hear talking to the chief priest, to Judas?
What does it gain a man to gain the whole world and yet forfeit his soul?
For what can a man give in return for his soul?
For whoever is ashamed of me and of my words in this adulterous and sinful generation,
of him the Son of Man will also be ashamed when he comes in glory.
Truly I say to you that there are some standing here who will not taste death until they see the kingdom of God after it has come in its power.
So, back to our question at the beginning.
Why does Jesus make such a big deal of Mary's action?
Why does he think that everyone across the whole world, across all time, when the gospel is preached, they need to hear this story?
Why?
Because Mary's action becomes for us the ideal response, the perfect demonstration of what discipleship to Jesus looks like.
A life rooted in sacrificial worship and totally surrendered to God's agenda.
I love how Dr. Tim Gombas puts it.
Jesus notes that she is preparing him for burial, indicating that she fully identifies herself and all that she has with the death of Jesus.
By doing so, she not only takes her place with other commendable characters in Mark's gospel,
but she stands as the supreme example of ideal discipleship.
The supreme example of ideal discipleship.
She publicly identifies with Jesus and his death at great personal cost and without reservation in the hope of resurrection.
My main point for this morning, the one thing that I want you to not forget, this is it.
Discipleship to Jesus that lasts is rooted in sacrificial worship and is totally surrendered to God's agenda.
This is why Jesus wants everybody that hears the gospel to hear the story of Mary, because she gets it.
And he wants us to get it.
Christ's intended response to the gospel of Jesus is total surrender to his agenda above our own.
It's allegiance to him as Lord.
It's trusting that his plans and purposes for our life are far better for us than our own.
Do you guys believe that?
It's quiet in here.
All right.
Not only was Mary's actions a beautiful picture.
This is going to be fun.
They should not trust me with this.
I don't know if they do.
I just didn't ask permission, so.
If Kevin's here, I did test this and the smoke alarm doesn't go off, hopefully.
If it does, then it's going to be fun.
I don't know.
Also, I did test it because I know some of you have pretty bad allergies.
The room's so big, you're probably not even going to be able to smell it.
I really want you to smell it, but you're probably not going to.
Okay.
Not only is Mary's actions a beautiful picture of the ideal response to the gospel of Jesus,
but I believe it will become a profound reminder of the beauty of the hope of the resurrection
for all of the people that were in that room.
There's this thing called the Proust effect.
Anybody heard of it?
It is a sudden or vivid memory triggered by scent.
And you guys ever walk by a tree, a breeze hits you a certain way,
and all of a sudden you're taken back to the elementary school playground or something.
Anybody experienced this before?
Scent is, it's literally scientifically proven that scent and memories are close to one another
in the brain, and somehow, I'm not smart, I'm not the guy to tell you the whole thing,
but just take my word for it.
A sudden and vivid memory triggered by scent.
What was the scent that Mary filled the room with?
Burial oils.
Mary's act of sacrificial worship filled the room with the aroma of burial oils.
The very same scent, listen to this, that every person in that room,
the disciples who judged her, who condemned her, who told her she was wrong,
for the rest of the aroma of death.
When they come face to face with death, when they come face to face with loss,
when they smell the aroma of death,
I think, I believe,
they're going to be triggered.
And a memory of this room
is going to pop into their brain.
And what are they going to be reminded of?
The hope of the resurrection.
Because Mary,
submitted to the agenda of Jesus,
prepares him for his burial.
He's going to go to the cross,
he's going to die,
he's going to be crucified,
he's going to be buried,
and three days later,
he's going to be raised,
and everyone in that room is going to know
that he has been raised from the dead.
And when they come
and encounter
death in their life,
they smell the aroma of burial,
they're going to be reminded that there's hope.
That death is not where things end.
That Jesus has conquered
sin, death,
and the grave,
and they can have hope
in the midst of their pain,
in the midst of their chaos.
I think they're going to be reminded
that if they just keep on trusting,
if they just keep on submitting,
Jesus wins in the end.
His agenda is worth following.
Paul says this in 1 Corinthians,
he says,
we are the aroma of Christ to God
among those who are being saved.
Mary became the aroma of Christ
to those in the room,
reminding them of the beauty
of following Jesus,
reminding them that submitting
their lives to Jesus is worth it,
is our discipleship to Jesus,
rooted in sacrificial worship
and total surrender.
April, you and the team can come up.
Are our lives the aroma of Christ
to those who are being saved?
Does the way we respond to Jesus
positively impact those
who are being drawn to him?
Or are we far more often
led by a spirit of self-righteousness,
judgmentalism,
or the pursuit of earthly pleasures
over kingdom obedience?
I think Mary's total surrender
set in the backdrop
of everyone else's desire for control
leaves us with a lot to think about.
I think it's why Jesus made sure
this story was preserved
for us this morning.
So, if you're in here
and you're a follower of Jesus,
I just want you to consider
in what ways
do you have the heart posture
of the chief priests
or the scribes
or the disciples
in the room
or Judas?
In what ways
is your agenda
not lining up
with Jesus' agenda?
In what ways
might your heart
be leading you
away from what God
has for you?
And if you're in here
and you're not
a follower of Jesus yet,
I'll just say this.
The gospel has been preached
in many ways
calling for many
different responses.
But I think this story
gives us a clear picture
of what the gospel is
and what Christ's invitation
to those who haven't
accepted him yet is.
Jesus has won
the victory over sin,
death,
and the grave
through facing it head on,
going straight to the cross,
willingly
and obediently.
His invitation to you
is to
take the posture
of Mary,
to trust him,
to die to yourself,
to relinquish control
of your life
and let him call
the shots.
If you're tired
of calling your own shots
and the results
haven't gotten you
where you think
they should,
today's the day
that you should submit
your life to Jesus.
It's been the best decision
I've ever made.
I've got no clue
where I'd be without him.
Discipleship to Jesus
that lasts
is rooted in sacrificial worship
and total surrender.
That's April
and the team
to lead us
in one final song
and I would just ask you
to consider that question
about which heart posture
is coming up in you.
Is it the chief priest?
Is it the scribes?
Is it Judas?
Is it the disciples
in the room?
Or is it a cocktail
of many of them?
Consider that
and consider what it might look like
to repent from that
and follow the example
of Mary
bowing at the feet of Jesus
totally surrendered
to his agenda.